<page><title>Revulytics</title><pageid>22305973</pageid><category>Software by company</category><sections><section title="">Revulytics (formerly V.I. Labs) is a privately held business intelligence company headquartered in Waltham, Massachusetts, United States. The company acquired Trackerbird Software Analytics, based in Malta, and re-branded on November 15, 2016. Revulytics provides business-to-business solutions to independent software vendors for software usage and software compliance reporting.
Revulytics clients operate in the Electronic Design Automation (EDA), Product Lifecycle Management (PLM), Computer-Aided Design (CAD), and other software spaces.


</section><section title="History and Products">Revulytics was founded in 2002 around interest in a software anti-piracy product. It then developed and introduced a different product in 2008 (originally named CodeArmor Intelligence) to report on the unlicensed use of client software; this product is now called Revulytics Compliance Intelligence, or RCI. RCI offers client companies the insight to understand their software piracy, and optionally enables conversion of unlicensed users into paying customers. Since 2010, Revulytics has supported its customers&#8217; compliance programs in generating more than $2.1 billion in new revenue. The RCI dashboard interface is built on Salesforce.
With the acquisition of Trackerbird Software Analytics in 2016, Revulytics expanded its offerings. Revulytics Usage Intelligence (or RUI) gives valuable insight into version adoption, feature usage, and user environments. It enables developers and product managers to make data-driven roadmap decisions, prioritize development resources, and optimize product and marketing strategies.


</section><section title="Partnerships">Salesforce.com V.i. Labs is a member of Salesforce.com&#8217;s ISV Application Partner Program, enabling the company to bundle, provision and centrally maintain a software intelligence dashboard for ISVs. The partnership allows for the integration of various data sets into standalone and existing salesforce.com instances for greater information sharing throughout an ISVs organization.
Microsoft V.i. Labs is a member of the Microsoft Windows Embedded Partner program, Microsoft Empower ISV Program, Visual Studio Industry Partners (VSIP) program, and participates in Microsoft Technology Adoption Programs.
Reprise Software V.i. Labs and Reprise Software have layered CodeArmor software protection with Reprise License Management (RLM) to address binary patching threats faced by ISVs.


</section><section title="Industry Affiliations">Software &amp; Information Industry Association (SIIA) The Software &amp; Information Industry Association (SIIA) is the principal trade association for the software and digital content industry. SIIA provides global services in government relations, business development, corporate education and intellectual property protection to more than 1000 leading software and information companies.
Electronic Design Automation Consortium (EDAC) The EDA Consortium is an international association of companies that provide tools and services that enable engineers to create the world's electronic products. EDA is the critical technology used to design electronics for the communications, computer, space technology, medical and industrial equipment and consumer electronics markets among others.
Federation Against Software Theft / Investors in Software (FAST IiS) The Federation Against Software Theft is a not-for-profit organization, formed in 1984 with the aim of eliminating copyright infringement of software in the UK. FAST was an early anti-piracy organization to work to protect the copyrights of software publishers. Initially concentrating on lobbying parliament to revise copyright law, FAST also prosecutes organizations and individuals for copyright infringement on behalf of its members.
Revulytics is a member of the Federation's Security Products and Services and Software Publishers groups.
The company also sponsors the Software Piracy Initiatives Forum (SPIF) on LinkedIn, which was created for discussion and professional networking between ISV employees involved in analyzing and addressing the impact of overt piracy and license overuse.


</section><section title="Accolades">In May 2010, V.i. Laboratories' CodeArmor Platform was selected by the Software and Information Industry Association as a winner of its CODiE Award for "Best DRM Solution."


</section><section title="Funding">Series A &#8211; Rockford Capital (June 2006)
Series B &#8211; Ascent Venture Partners, Core Capital Partners &#8211; $8 million (November 2007)
Expanded Series B &#8211; Ascent Venture Partners, Core Capital Partners &#8211; $4 million (October 2008)


</section></sections></page>