<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1251"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
	<title>Reuters News</title>
	<link></link>
	<description>Reuters.com is your source for breaking news, business, financial and investing news, including personal finance and stocks.  Reuters is the leading global provider of news, financial information and technology solutions to the world's media, financial institutions, businesses and individuals.</description>
	<language>en-us</language>

<item>
	<title>Iraqi military pushes deeper into Mosul's Old City</title>
	<description>MOSUL, Iraq (Reuters) - Iraq's military pushed deeper into Mosul's Old City on Wednesday, taking two more districts from Islamic State and bringing it closer to total control of the city.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/6bhh_JdaIbc/uk-mideast-crisis-iraq-mosul-idUKKBN19J1LI</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-mideast-crisis-iraq-mosul-idUKKBN19J1LI?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 15:13:22 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>North Korea calls for execution of ex-South Korea leader over 'assassination' plot</title>
	<description>SEOUL (Reuters) - North Korea said on Wednesday it has issued a standing order for the execution of former South Korean President Park Geun-hye and her spy chief for a plot to assassinate its leader, and it demanded that the South hand the pair over.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/mYMFgA64klU/uk-northkorea-southkorea-execution-idUKKBN19J1KB</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-northkorea-southkorea-execution-idUKKBN19J1KB?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 14:06:38 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Venezuela hunts rogue helicopter attackers, Maduro foes smell rat</title>
	<description>CARACAS (Reuters) - The Venezuelan government hunted on Wednesday for rogue policemen who attacked key installations by helicopter, but critics of President Nicolas Maduro suspected the raid may have been manipulated to justify repression.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UK</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-venezuela-politics-idUKKBN19I2S3?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:40:27 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>U.S. says its warning appears to have averted Syrian chemical attack</title>
	<description>BRUSSELS/ISTANBUL (Reuters) - U.S. Defence Secretary Jim Mattis said on Wednesday that the Syrian government of President Bashar al-Assad appeared so far to have heeded a warning this week from Washington not to carry out a chemical weapons attack.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/SweSD6J4vT0/uk-mideast-crisis-syria-idUKKBN19J1TX</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-mideast-crisis-syria-idUKKBN19J1TX?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:00:16 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>New computer virus spreads from Ukraine to disrupt world business</title>
	<description>FRANKFURT/MOSCOW/KIEV (Reuters) - A new cyber virus spread from Ukraine to wreak havoc around the globe on Wednesday, crippling thousands of computers, disrupting ports from Mumbai to Los Angeles and halting production at a chocolate factory in Australia.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/hUo-Kvwx82k/uk-cyber-attack-idUKKBN19J16K</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-cyber-attack-idUKKBN19J16K?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:57:24 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Pro-Trump groups take no prisoners in rush to help an embattled president</title>
	<description>WASHINGTON (Reuters) - Flush with cash, political groups outside the White House are aggressively coming to President Donald Trump's aid as he battles low public approval numbers, questions about his election campaign's ties to Russia and a stalled legislative agenda.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/W5kJ_uy-a7c/uk-usa-trump-super-pacs-idUKKBN19J2G2</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-usa-trump-super-pacs-idUKKBN19J2G2?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:50:01 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>More Venezuelan children dying from preventable diseases amid crisis</title>
	<description>CARACAS/LA GUAJIRA, Venezuela (Reuters) - Twelve-year-old Samuel Becerra went to Venezuela's main paediatric hospital for routine dialysis in March.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/zN0basLNcCw/uk-venezuela-politics-children-idUKKBN19J2FD</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-venezuela-politics-children-idUKKBN19J2FD?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:48:47 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>U.N. rapporteur, media watchdog slam Qatar-based Al Jazeera closure demands</title>
	<description>DUBAI (Reuters) - A United Nations expert and a media freedom watchdog on Wednesday criticised four Arab states for seeking to close Al Jazeera television in a rift with Qatar.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/5ugY8njajcM/uk-gulf-qatar-jazeera-idUKKBN19J2HM</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-gulf-qatar-jazeera-idUKKBN19J2HM?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:57:48 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Protests held across India after attacks against Muslims</title>
	<description>NEW DELHI/MUMBAI (Reuters) - Protests were held in cities across India on Wednesday against a wave of attacks on Muslims by mobs that accuse them of killing cows or eating beef.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/9HU1G41vA0Y/uk-india-protests-idUKKBN19J2C1</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-india-protests-idUKKBN19J2C1?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 17:52:58 +0100</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Clergy at Catholic monastery in Vietnam say were assaulted over land dispute</title>
	<description>HANOI (Reuters) - Catholic clergy in a monastery in Vietnam said they were beaten by people they believed were plain clothes police on Wednesday in an on-going land dispute.</description>
	<link>http://feeds.reuters.com/~r/Reuters/UKWorldNews/~3/9MPADCx9Nmk/uk-vietnam-politics-landrights-idUKKBN19J2FB</link>
	<guid>http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-vietnam-politics-landrights-idUKKBN19J2FB?feedType=RSS</guid>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 18:49:33 +0100</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
