<page><title>Biscom</title><pageid>13891636</pageid><category>Companies of Taiwan</category><sections><section title="">Biscom, Inc. is a privately held enterprise software company with headquarters in Chelmsford, MA, and with a satellite office in Taipei City, Taiwan. Biscom&#8217;s primary focus is developing fax server solutions that facilitate inbound and outbound electronic fax communications. Biscom also develops managed file transfer and data conversion solutions.
Biscom was founded in 1986 by S.K. Ho, currently Biscom's CEO. S.K. Ho was formerly the Director of Engineering at Wang Laboratories, where he designed and developed the Wang Word Processor and Wang Professional Image Systems; he holds nine major patents. Mr. Ho earned a BSME from Ordinance Engineering College in Taiwan and an MSEE from Drexel University.


</section><section title="Biscom Launches Fax Server Industry">Recognizing the opportunity to combine facsimile communications with computer applications, S.K. Ho left Wang Laboratories to found Biscom, Inc., and thus he launched the fax server industry. Early application of Biscom&#8217;s fax server, the FAXCOM Server, applied print output from mainframe applications to an electronic form, and merged this into a single TIFF document which could be delivered electronically via fax. This was a vast improvement over earlier processes in which the mainframe data would be printed to paper forms, and then mailed or sent via paper fax machine.


</section><section title="Fax Server Industry Evolves">Fax server solutions have continually evolved since 1986, supporting desktop faxing via email, via Web browser, and via Application Programming Interfaces (APIs); integrating with directory services such as Microsoft&#8217;s Active Directory and Novell&#8217;s eDirectory; integrating with Voice over IP (VoIP) to support T.38 Fax over IP (FoIP); supporting paper-based faxing via multi function printers; enabling fax workflows with support for Optical Character Recognition (OCR) and barcode interpretation for rules based fax routing; and offering fax server capabilities in both premises and hosted solutions.


</section><section title="Biscom Expands Product Lines">Biscom has evolved into a provider of multiple product lines, including Managed File Transfer solutions that enable secure and auditable delivery of files of all types and sizes, and Image Conversion solutions that convert to and from popular formats such as PCL (Printer Command Language), PostScript, PDF (Portable Document Format), and Microsoft Office, and Enterprise File Synchronization &amp; Sharing solutions that enable full IT control of data and user manageability.


</section></sections></page>