<page><title>Comparison of shopping cart software</title><pageid>18535598</pageid><category>E-commerce</category><sections><section title="">The following is a comparison of the features of notable shopping cart software packages available. Some such shopping cart software is extensible through third-party software components and applications. As such, the features listed below may not encompass all possible features for a given software package. The software listed here is but a fraction of all such packages on the market.


</section><section title="General information">Basic information about the shopping carts including creator, software license and framework, and updates.


</section><section title="Data storage">Information about what data storage system can be used.


</section><section title="General features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Customer features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Customer reward features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Administration area features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Search engine optimization features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Security features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Other features">Information about the features the shopping carts offer.


</section><section title="Payment gateway support">Information about which payment gateways are supported.


</section><section title="Alternative checkout support">Information about which alternative checkouts are supported.


</section><section title="Real-time shipping calculation">Information about if shopping carts have real-time shipping calculation built-in to allow calculating how much it will cost to ship an order in real time when the customer checks out an order.


</section><section title="Shipment booking integration">Information about if shopping carts have shipment booking integration to allow staff to be able to book shipments for a number of orders at once via the control panel.


</section><section title="Shipment tracking integration">Information about if shopping carts have shipment tracking integration to show the customers the tracking information on the "View order" pages.


</section></sections></page>