<page><title>SaferVPN</title><pageid>55440919</pageid><category>Software</category><sections><section title="">SaferVPN is a Virtual Private Network utility developed by Safer Social, Ltd. The network protects user data from Wi-Fi security risks through end-to-end encryption of user connections. SaferVPN has provided free accounts to dissidents in Turkey, Iran, and Bangladesh.


</section><section title="History">SaferVPN was released in 2013 by cybersecurity software developers, including founders Amit Bareket and Sagi Gidali. SaferVPN&#8217;s parent company began raising capital after creating and patenting a system created to aid law enforcement in identifying and catching car thieves. In the Microsoft Imagine Cup competition the first application cofounders Amit Bareket and Sagi Gidali assembled together made second place.


=== #UnblockTheWeb ===
In March 2014 when Turkey attempted to block Twitter, SaferVPN launched the #UnblockTheWeb initiative to give individuals blocked by government censorship free access to a VPN. In August, 2016, Unblock the Web provided a free VPN account to a coalition of Bangladeshi bloggers allowing them to communicate. In 2016, Apple approved SaferVPN to implement automatic Wi-Fi Security. Its patented technology alerts users when they connect to an unsecured Wi-Fi network even if their device is locked, preventing harmful data leaks.


</section><section title="Technology">SaferVPN uses protocols to secure data that is transmitted over its network. Each protocol varies in how the data is secured. SaferVPN&#8217;s supported protocols include:
OpenVPN, the commonly used protocol due to its performance and security level.
Point-To-Point Tunneling Protocol (PPTP), a commonly used VPN protocol that uses basic encryption giving users fast connection speeds.
Layer 2 Tunneling Protocol (L2TP/IPSec), secure but slower than other protocols. L2TP is a good option if OpenVPN or IKEv2 aren&#8217;t available. Unlike PPTP, L2TP/IPSec requires a shared key or the use of certificates.
IKEv2, the newest protocol available. Fastest of all protocols, it is secure and stable but not supported on all platforms.


</section></sections></page>