<page><title>Comparison of genealogy software</title><pageid>6840228</pageid><category>Genealogy software</category><sections><section title="">This article compares several selected client-based genealogy programs. Web-based genealogy software is not included.


</section><section title="General information">

</section><section title="General features">Genealogy software products differ in the way they support data acquisition (e.g. drag and drop data entry for images, flexible data formats, free defined custom attributes for persons and connections between persons, rating of sources) and interaction (e.g. 3D-view, name filters, full text search and dynamic pan and zoom navigation), in reporting (e.g.: fan charts, automatic narratives, relationship between arbitrary people, place of birth on virtual globes, statistics about number of children per family), validation (e.g.: consistency checks, research assistants connected to online genealogy databases), exporting (e.g.: export as web page, book or wall chart) and integration (e.g.: synchronisation with tablet version). Some software might include also fun and entertainment features (e.g. quizzes or slideshows).


</section><section title="Genealogical features">Besides exchange between systems (e.g. GEDCOM support for import and export), flexible data handling (e.g. custom attributes and multiple kinds of relations between people) is relevant.


</section><section title="Languages">Available user interface languages
a Agelong Tree is also available in Arabic, Armenian, Bashkir, Belarusian, Bulgarian, Catalan, Chinese, Circassian, Croatian, Czech, Estonian, Galician, Georgian, Greek, Hungarian, Latvian, Lithuanian, Romanian, Serbian, Slovak, Tajik, Tatar, Turkish, Turkmen, Ukrainian and Uzbek.
b Can be created by available translation program or language file.
c Ahnenblatt is also available in Croatian, Czech, Estonian, Hungarian, Portuguese, Romanian and Turkish.
d Ancestral Quest also has partial translations in Chinese (Traditional) and Finnish.
e Ancestris is also available in Portuguese and Greek.
f Genbox Family History is also available in Slovak, Slovenian; partial translations are available for Czech, Greek, Hungarian, Lithuanian, Portuguese, and Vietnamese.
g Can be created using the built-in translation tables.
h GenoPro is also available in Arabic, Catalan, Czech, Estonian, Finnish, Greek, Hungarian, Latvian/Lettish and Vietnamese. Partial translations are available in Portuguese (Brazil), Indonesian, Dutch, Hebrew, Swedish, Portuguese (Portugal), Lithuanian, Turkish, Chinese Traditional/Taiwan (Big5), Albanian, Ukrainian, Croatian, Bulgarian, Icelandic, Scots Gaelic, Chinese simplified (Gb3312).
i Gramps is also available in Catalan, Czech, Esperanto, Finnish, Greek, Hungarian, Lithuanian, Portuguese (Brazil), Portuguese (Portugal), Slovak, Slovenian, and Ukrainian. Partial translations are available in Arabic, Bulgarian, Chinese, Croatian, Vietnamese, and 11 more languages translated less than 50%.
j Includes Australian English, Canadian English, UK English, and US English.
k Includes both nynorsk and bokm&#229;l.
l English is the only language officially supported by the vendor of Reunion, but instructions for producing a translation are included, and users have made available the indicated translations.
m My Family Tree also has complete translations in English (Australian), Portuguese (Brazil and Portugal variants) and partial translations in Arabic (Saudi Arabian), Chinese (Traditional), Chinese (Simplified), Turkish, Vietnamese, Finnish and Uyghur.
n Includes UK English and US English.
o Ages! is also available in Catalan, Czech, Finnish, Greek, Portuguese and Ukrainian.


</section></sections></page>